Was bedeutete es für den Alltag vor dem 7. Oktober, in unmittelbarer Nähe zu Gaza und unter einer dauerhaften Sicherheitsbedrohung leben?
That's a very important question,
because it makes you understand
why there is such a huge gap
between the number of casualties here,
and the other side, that's one of the reason.
Firstly...
my government takes care of me.
If you walk around the kibbutz,
you will see, every house has a bomb shelter,
as one of the bedrooms is a bomb shelter.
I have bomb shelters scattered around the kibbutz,
anywhere, if you look around now,
you will spot a few.
Thirdly...
I get messages straight to my phone.
If the army spots something,
"Take shelter" or "be next to a safe room" or whatever.
So my government does a lot,
not that specific government,
but Israeli governments in general,
as a democratic state should do,
they take care of us,
and they give us the means to protect ourselves.
If you walk around,
if I walked around the kibbutz with you,
I could even show you
the different stages of fortifying
because the threats change and
they became a lot more serious throughout the years,
and as the threat change, also the fortifying changes.
So, that's about living here.
Besides ...
Let's say that I don’t live in this place,
and I go to live in Jerusalem or Tel Aviv,
or any other place in Israel,
You have people coming with knives
to make terror attacks, you have bombs,
you have guns, you have trucks
driving into crowds, you have...
booby trap balloons that come over,
Burning kites,
to burn the wheat that we very hard...
worked for.
Looking at this,
you can understand why the border is closed
from the Israeli side and from the Egyptian side.
Because
if everything you’re capable of doing is killing,
stealing,
and burning in your neighbor's land,
nobody wants to have anything to do with you.
Nobody wants anything to do with you.
That is unbelievable to see.
As I said I come from the left of the politics,
I've always cared a lot about
the people on the other side.
I still do.
I'm not stupid enough
to think that 2 million people were
all created the same and they all want to kill me.
But we have a serious problem here,
because when you have a ruler...
Two examples:
You have a ruler,
you’re saying that you’re ruling a starving population.
In 2005, when Israel withdrew from the Gaza Strip.
Israel left...
Greenhouses abundant with fruit and vegetables.
What they did the second that Israel went out?
and they left it for them,
it was a flourishing market.
The second that Israel left,
they came with bats,
and they smashed the entire thing down.
That's the first example that shook my world,
the picture of that was like "what?".
Let's say somebody came here and occupied my people,
and then when they left,
they left us a huge pile of gold,
and we just
decide to take it and throw it into the ocean.
The second thing were the terror attack tunnels.
When I saw the size of the tunnels,
when I saw how much money,
and how many resources were spent to do that
in order, again,
to kill and steal in the neighboring countries.
so I'm asking...
I have a very humanitarian heart,
and my first thoughts about the tunnels were,
before 2014, were "Okay. they're poor people",
"they probably need aid and they probably need"
"medications so they have their tunnels."
That was my excuse for it. and then after those
deadly attacks that happened
both in Egypt and in Israel,
way before October 7,
I looked at this and I said okay,
"I also have a brain", haha,
and this brain has some questions,
because I figured out how much money,
I found it out, how much money it costs to build it,
and I'm saying "what the hell".
What are you talking about?
Why aren't you building...
Why aren't you building dairy farms,
and henneries and schools and hospitals?
Why aren't you planting crops?
All you can do is burn the crops of your neighbors,
with those burning kites.
That's all you do? We sit on the same land.
How come we make agriculture and you’re not,
not on the same level.
And, I'm sorry to tell you,
but when you choose destruction over construction
over and over again
you will probably not be
the most flourishing nation on planet earth.
What can you do, this is how life works.
I don’t know.
What are you doing?
You have a starving population? Feed them.
You’re getting so much aid? Feed them.
But, again
It’s a lie,
because the population in Gaza is not starving,
never have been starving.
But if a ruler claims something like that,
his actions should fit the narrative he's trying to...
I always hear the
spokespeople for Hamas say "what could we have done?".
"What could we have done?" Very simple:
You could have acknowledged the fact that
there's the state of Israel and that
minorities in the Middle East are allowed to rule
a tiny piece of land.
That's very easy what you could have done.